A Finding Aid to the 3EP Ltd. Records, 1970-1984, bulk 1979-1984, in the Archives of American Art AAA.3epltd
Archives of American Art
3EP Ltd. records
bulk 1979-1984
1970-1984
AAA.3epltd
Archives of American Art
4.3 Linear feet
The records of California fine arts print publisher 3EP Ltd. founded by Moo (Mary Margaret) Anderson, Joseph Goldyne, and Paula Kirkeby measure 4.3 linear feet and date from 1970 to 1984. The records include scattered administrative files; artists' files that include correspondence, lists, price lists, and miscellany; printed materials, photographs, including two dismantled photo albums and negatives; and numerous fine arts prints by various contemporary artists, including Gordon Cook, Claire Falkenstein, Joe Fay, Sam Francis, David Gilhooly, Joseph Goldyne, Jack Jefferson, Frank Lobdell, Fred Martin, Ed Moses, Nathan Oliveira, Jay Phillips, Matt Phillips, and Joseph Zirker.
3EP Ltd..
Anderson, Mary Margaret
Kirkeby, Paula
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 5 series.
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1978-1984 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Artists Files, 1970-1984 (1.8 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1981-1984 (0.1 linear feet; Box 3)
Series 4: Artwork, 1979-1984 (1.9 linear feet; OV 4-22)
Series 5: Photographic Material, 1981-1983 (0.3 linear feet; Box 3)
Biographical/Historical note
3EP Ltd. was founded by Moo (Mary Margaret) Anderson, Joseph Goldyne, and Paula Kirkeby in 1978 in Palo Alto, California. The print publisher worked with over 20 artists to produce fine art prints and monotypes and operated until 1984.
Harry W. and Mary Margaret Anderson, respectively known as Hunk and Moo, are avid art collectors with one of the largest private art collections of 20th Century American Art. Moo has a special interest in works of art on paper and prints. Moo and Paula Kirkeby, director of Smith Anderson Gallery in Palo Alto, along with San Francisco artist Joseph Goldyne formed 3EP Ltd. In addition to sales, the mission of 3EP Ltd. was to encourage experimentation with the monoprint. Anderson and Kirkeby commissioned a custom-built Takach-Garfield press for their facilities and invited artists to work with the monotype technique and printmaking, techniques that were initially unfamiliar to many of the artists who worked with 3EP Ltd. Artists invited to work at 3EP include Gordon Cook, Claire Falkenstein, Joe Fay, Sam Francis, David Gilhooly, Frank Lobdell, Ed Moses, Nathan Oliviera, Jay and Matt Phillips, and many others. 3EP Ltd. closed in 1984.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. research facility.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of the collection are also available on 35 mm microfilm reels 3534-3536 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers are advised that the order of microfilm no longer matches the order of the arranged collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The 3EP Ltd. records were donated in 1984 by Moo (Mary Margaret) Anderson and Paula Kirkeby. Plates received with the donation were returned to the donors.
Related Archival Materials note
The de Young Museum has a collection of 3EP Ltd. prints which are part of the Anderson Graphic Arts Collection.
Scope and Contents note
The records of California fine arts print publisher 3EP Ltd. founded by Moo (Mary Margaret) Anderson, Joseph Goldyne, and Paula Kirkeby measure 4.3 linear feet and date from 1970 to 1984. The records include scattered administrative files; artists' files that include correspondence, lists, price lists, and miscellany; printed materials, photographs, including two dismantled photo albums and negatives; and numerous fine arts prints by various contemporary artists, including Gordon Cook, Claire Falkenstein, Joe Fay, Sam Francis, David Gilhooly, Joseph Goldyne, Jack Jefferson, Frank Lobdell, Fred Martin, Ed Moses, Nathan Oliveira, Jay Phillips, Matt Phillips, and Joseph Zirker.
Administrative records consist of chronological correspondence, subscriber lists and forms, price lists, exhibition lists, and other miscellaneous records. Business/administrative correspondence is mostly between the 3EP Ltd. founders and various museums, galleries, and collectors, with a few letters to artists. Artists' files include resumes, correspondence, catalogs, clippings, photographs and slides. Artists include Chuck Arnoldi, Billy Al Bengston, Gordon Cook, Claire Falkenstein, Joe Fay, Sam Francis, Jack Jefferson, Frank Lobdell, Ed Moses, George Sugarman, and Joseph Zirker, among many others.
Arnoldi, Charles, 1946-; Bengston, Billy Al; Cook, Gordon; Falkenstein, Claire, 1908-1997; Fay, Joe, 1950-; Francis, Sam, 1923-1994; Gilhooly, David; Goldyne, Joseph R.; Jefferson, Jack, 1921-2000; Lobdell, Frank, 1921-; Martin, Fred; Moses, Ed, 1926-; Olivera, Nathan; Phillips, Jay, 1954-1987; Phillips, Matt; Sugarman, George, 1912-1999; Zirker, Joseph; Art publishing--California--Palo Alto; Graphic arts; Intaglio printing; Photograph albums; Photographs; Printmakers--California; Prints; Prints--20th century
- Administrative Records, 1978-1984; Series 1; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Administrative records consist of chronological correspondence, subscriber lists and agreement forms, price lists, letterhead samples, exhibition lists, miscellaneous notes, and other business material. The correspondence is mostly between the 3EP Ltd. founders and various museums, galleries, and collectors on the subject of prints and billing, along with a few letters to artists.
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5-8)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Undated Correspondence, 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Subscribers Lists, circa 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Subscribers Agreement Forms, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Subscribers Agreement Forms, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Subscribers Agreement Forms, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Price Lists of Artwork, circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Price Lists of Artwork, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Terms of Agreement for Work with Artists, circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Exhibitions List, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letterhead and Business Cards, circa 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Glossary of Printmaking Terms, circa 1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Promotional Material and Mission Statement, circa 1981 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Artists Files, 1970-1984; Series 2; 1.8 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Artists' files include resumes, correspondence, exhibition announcements, catalogs, invoices, curatorial sheets with information on artwork, clippings, photographs, and slides of artwork. Notable artists include Chuck Arnoldi, Billy Al Bengston, Gordon Cook, Laddie John Dill, Claire Falkenstein, Joe Fay, Sam Francis, David Gilhooly, Joseph Goldyne, Russel T. Gordon, Jules Heller, Tom Holland, Jack Jefferson, Frank Lobdell, Fred Martin, Ed Moses, Nathan Oliviera, Jay Phillips, Matt Phillips, Miklos Pogany, Inez Storer, Joseph Zirker, and others.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Arnoldi, Chuck, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Bengston, Billy Al, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
  - Cook, Gordon, circa 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Dill, Laddie John, circa 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 30-35)
  - Falkenstein, Claire, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - Fay, Joe, circa 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Francis, Sam, circa 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 40-47)
  - Gilhooly, David, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 48-50)
  - Goldyne, Joseph, circa 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Gordon, Russell T., 1973-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Heller, Jules, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Holland, Tom, 1970-1982 (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
  - Jefferson, Jack, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Lobdell, Frank, 1981-1984 (Box 2, Folder 11-14)
  - Martin, Fred, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - Moses, Ed, circa 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 17-26)
  - Oliviera, Nathan, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
  - Phillips, Jay, circa 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 29-33)
  - Phillips, Matt, 1974-1984 (Box 2, Folder 34-38)
  - Pogany, Miklos, circa 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 39-40)
  - Storer, Inez, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Sugarman, George, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Zirker, Joseph, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 43-44)
- Printed Material, 1981-1984; Series 4; 0.1 Linear feet Box 3
  Printed material consists of a few exhibition announcements, catalogs, and clippings.
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - News Clippings, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Artwork, 1979-1984; Series 4; 1.9 Linear feet OV 4-22
  Artwork includes numerous fine arts prints by 14 artists. Several of the folders include curatorial sheets with information about the prints, such as the medium, title, and date of individual prints.
  The artwork is arranged alphabetically by artist's surname.
  - Gordon Cook Prints, 1984 (Box OV 4)
    Includes 1 print titled Point Richmond.
  - Claire Falkenstein Prints, 1981 (Box OV 5)
    Includes 2 prints titled Allegory 4 and Allegory 5.
  - Joe Fay Artwork, circa 1982 (Box OV 6)
    Includes painted boards cut into various shapes and one untitled print.
  - Joe Fay Artwork, circa 1982 (Box OV 7)
    Includes sketches in pencil and 1 untitled print.
  - Sam Francis Prints, 1981-1982 (Box OV 8-9)
    Includes numerous prints titled Pivot, Tar Flower, Self Portrait, and several untitled prints.
  - David Gilhooly Prints, 1983 (Box OV 10-11)
    Includes several prints titled Food Descending the Staircase, My Daily Bread, The First Morning Cup of Paula's Coffee, and Selbstbildnis mit Tod. There are more multiple versions of some prints.
  - Joseph Goldyne Prints, 1979 (Box OV 12)
    Includes 3 impressions each of two prints titled Dirty Dish and Garbage Can.
  - Jack Jefferson Prints, 1981 (Box OV 13)
    Includes 2 untitled prints.
  - Frank Lobdell Prints, 1981 (Box OV 14)
    Includes 9 untitled prints.
  - Fred Martin Prints, 1980 (Box OV 15)
    Includes Tarot of California, a portfolio of six prints, and 3 reproductions of a cover sheet for the portfolio along with the original version of the cover sheet with a pasted-in negative of the cover image.
  - Ed Moses Prints, 1980-1983 (Box OV 16-17)
    Includes the following prints: EM G-1, EM G-2, EM G-3, EM G-5, P-Bl (2 prints), Bite Head II, Noh-bu Wall A, Noh-bu Wall B, Noh-Bu Wall C, Portrait, Krak WI I, Krak WI II, Krak WI III, and several untitled prints.
  - Nathan Oliviera Prints, 1979 (Box OV 18)
    Includes 6 prints titled Archive Site, Emerson Site 1, and Emerson Site 2.
  - Jay Phillips Prints, 1982-1983 (Box OV 19-20)
    Includes 13 prints total, some titled Beverly and Melrose, others untitled.
  - Matt Phillips Prints, 1979-1984 (Box OV 21)
    Includes 2 prints titled New York Recalled and Sighs and Whispers.
  - Joseph Zirker Print, 1981-1982 (Box OV 22)
    Includes 1 print titled Cosmic Entity.
- Photographic Material, 1981-1983; Series 5; 0.3 Linear feet Box 3
  Photographic material includes 2 dismantled photograph albums that depict the delivery of the custom-built printing press to 3EP Ltd. facilities, and portraits of various artists, such as Sam Francis, Jules Heller, and Joseph Zirker, at work on prints alongside master printers employed by the print publisher. There are also negatives of the photos in the albums, and one folder of an exhibition of 3EP Ltd. prints at a gallery.
  The photograph albums were dismantled prior to their arrival at the archives, and the order of the photographs was preserved in the folders during preliminary arrangement by a previous archivist.
  - Album 1, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 4-12)
    Includes photographs of Joseph Goldyne, Nathan Oliviera, Joseph Zirker, Sam Francis, Fred Martin, Frank Lobdell, and Inez Storer. Also includes photographs of Paula Kirkeby, Moo Anderson, and 3EP Ltd. master printmaker Ikuru Komahara.
  - Negatives from Album 1, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Album 2, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
    Includes photographs of Laddie John Dill, David Gilhooly, Ed Moses, and Jay Phillips.
  - Negatives from Album 2, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - 3EP Ltd. Exhibition at Gump's Gallery, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 17)